[Music]
the stoa
is a digital campfire where we cohere in
dialogue
about what matters most at the knife's
edge of what's happening now
hello everybody and welcome to the stoa
my name is raven connolly
um i'm a host here at the stoa and the
stoa is a digital campfire where we
gather to
go here and dialogue about what matters
most
at the knife's edge of this moment and
this is
an event um that i've been co-hosting
with
rachel haywire who will be joining us
shortly
uh called the philosopher queens uh and
we have been
discussing the metaphysical and kind of
like imminent
qualities of the feminine what are the
rising feminine
archetypes right now um how are we
understanding ourselves as women and
what all of the kind of
uh difficult questions there are about
addressing
those issues and today we are joined
with
nina power who is a cultural critic
philosopher ex-academic um she's written
a lot about feminism
and i'm super excited to have
nina i was in her course on batai that
she just did
with justin murphy so um very excited to
have you here
with us today nina thank you
yeah thank you so i wanted to start just
by like framing the situation
because from from my point of view there
seems to be
a lot of conflict around
what what a woman is who a woman is and
this to me seems to be an issue of
the kind of symptomatic uh liberation of
a woman you know the fact that we have
intervention into our biology that
allows us to choose
our kind of reproductive condition we
can move into the workforce
there's all of these kind of
unprecedented conditions that have been
afforded to us
by the kind of techno-capitalist world
that we've inherited
and it seems like in the culture we're
seeing the symptoms of that
with this uh very
you know contentious conversations
around
who is a woman who gets to be in women's
spaces what is it to be a woman
and also the contested kind of
relationship
of that term to biology and to sex
and so i wanted to start off the
conversation with that very base and
basic question
and to kind of see what is your
diagnosis where do you start when
thinking about
what is a woman sure
yeah i mean it's it's obviously an
extremely kind of contentious and
emotional topic and you know very
politically fraught and has been the
subject of a lot of kind of
uh i don't know often quite vicious um
arguments i mean i think my starting
point when you're
you know introducing this question is is
almost to think
in terms of a kind of recent history and
to think about
this question almost generationally like
you know i'm
generation x like born in the 70s and
you know and i think what i feel like
we've seen in in my lifetime
at you know and many other people's i
suppose
is a kind of fracturing of these terms
in certain ways so i mean it was
i think the second wave idea that there
was
you know sexual difference and there
were men and women
and that gender was this kind of social
force that was kind of negatively
imposed on the outside and it would kind
of
and it would be about certain
expectations that would kind of
attach themselves to sex as it were
right so the idea that if you were born
female then you were supposed to be this
kind of
person and if you're born male 1
especially this kind of person you know
and so gender was this kind of external
force but
sex wasn't kind of contested in the same
way as it was today it was just a kind
of fact a kind of brute
biological fact right you were born male
or female and
but actually there was a kind of
existentialist dimension which was kind
of
like to say but that tells you nothing
about how you're actually going to live
your
life you know it's up to you in a way so
i think the second wave
um actually had quite a kind of uh
trickle-down effect
on the way in which that idea permeate
permeated
however uh gently in education and
culture
and then i think that kind of shifted
something kind of happened in the last
10 years and i
you know i wrote this book in 2009
called one dimensional woman
which which is just a kind of short
polemic really about the kind of
consumer feminism and it was a kind of
against the way in which
capitalism seemed to be kind of trying
to integrate women into the workforce
and into this kind of capitalist subject
and
you know it was a kind of marcus against
the modern world
a kind of left refusal um of of that
um idea that feminism and capitalism
were um compatible
but it's interesting looking at that now
because i didn't discuss this question
of gender at all i basically took it for
granted that we knew what we were
talking about when we were talking about
men and women
um you know and that what we were
talking about was where the cultural
and economic aspects of how that played
out but
but the kind of the terms themselves
weren't in contestation
so something definitely happened in that
sort of
10-year period in which i would say
there are at least kind of two
definitions of gender at work you know
one of which was this kind of second
wave
definite the idea that gender was a kind
of imposition and
and ultimately that was something that
needed to be abolished or eliminated you
know the the second word position is
really that
gender was a negative thing you know
these expectations were bad for both
boys and girls and men and women and
actually what you wanted to do was
expand
uh you know the expressive possibilities
of sexuality and
uh and and habits and hobbies and and
love and all these other things and and
so people should be able to
you know do whatever they wanted kind of
regardless of sex as it were
um but then i think it's it's become
more obvious that there's a kind of
second
uh antagonistic concept of gender which
doesn't mat doesn't work with the other
one and it and it's kind of tried to
replace it
in lots of ways which is this idea
perhaps of a gender as an inner feeling
you know something that is um
an identity and i think we didn't i
you know my generation didn't grow up
with that idea of identity and this
touches on
this question more broadly not just to
do with sex
but you know the the idea that one is
one's identity as opposed to what one
does or
you know that i think we were much more
used to this idea of becoming rather
than being
something um and i you know there's a
big a big question about the kind of
technology you know what does it mean to
kind of live in such a
a separated way in the mind body sort of
split or the kind of
image feeling of self split online where
people are kind of constantly
you know there's a felt need to present
oneself
as a thing you know as a kind of
circulating identity
uh in this kind of playground um which
which oddly seems to have kind of become
very fixed
um you know and and people become very
territorial and
proprietorial about identity um
which you know i'm i'm very against and
i think
it doesn't it doesn't make sense for for
someone of
my generation to think like that um at
all and if we had an identity it was
something
like a kind of shared uselessness you
know like everyone was a bit rubbish and
that was quite good and i think
in the 90s there was a kind of humor was
much more about like everyone and
everything could be mocked
and there was like in a nice way you
know and that everybody was kind of um
yeah i mean potentially uh could laugh
at
oneself and i think something like
that's become lost it's become very
people have become very rigid and uh
possessive
um about this so i mean to go back to
your question i just think
you know like we there's i think it's
not controversial to say that there are
at least these two definitions of gender
that are
incompatible and that this is partly at
the root of what's going on
in all of these debates about who who
can and can't call themselves a woman or
what does this
woman mean i mean the contemporary
definition seems to be
if you ask who is a woman it's not you
know
that uh part of humanity that has large
gametes
right as opposed to small gametes which
would be the biological
definition it would be anyone who says
they are a woman
is a woman but of course this is a
circular definition
right so there's no content to that it's
simply a kind of assertion
um that fits with a kind of very uh
asatoric definitive notion of language
that language is this kind of possessive
identitarian
object that one can simply claim and
pluck out of
the air which is points to a broader
shift in language
and language use and concept use in
general which isn't necessarily
great i would say i
would love to segue from this subject to
an incredible poem
uh nina power wrote it's from her
platform so it's just all of you picked
this amazing people
my co-host by the way i
wish you my talk ravens he witnessed me
trying to find the right top and then i
tried to find the right
zoom room so here we are
raven is the older philosopher queen
today for being my shirt
and i'm the young philosopher and heard
the poem
this is fine by nina power
the man i am which one
the one you love the good one
me without you quietly
happily what isn't here
no concern what you can't
see the darkness
what words can't say
if you are zero
what escapes pick your jailer
jerks a gesture you can go it alone
at the outside nature
is two tired pilgrims
the tower is burning
to the tower came the sky is folly
this one to that one we are not the same
i'm smarter than you undoubtedly
they answer does it matter they decide
to stay the night
great yeah it's a very different
register of things thank you for reading
that
um rachel i like your uh philosophical
castle
yeah having this book exchange review
after
the elixir spawn made me so happy
because i've been wanting to
do work with you in one way or another
um
you're on justin murphy's show and
that's because there's a lot of
just interesting women and and this
sector
you know of this like idw intellectual
virus world
i would call it um and me and raven
we've always been just like
it's not about fitting a quota you know
i'm getting my woman it's about finding
women like us
you know and that's why when i release
the manifesto and raven asks
you guys in the piano we're like yeah we
were going to do this piano
to bring women who get it that are on
this
level this heightened state of being
and we are happy to be graced
with your presence here i had a
question for you um about the famous
you i'm sure you get asked a lot but
what was it to
work what was it like to to work with
video
what is it like to work with him to work
with baju
oh yeah i mean i guess this was a long
time ago
uh now when i was like a master student
um yeah he's an extremely affable man
right he's a kind of like jolly giant
he's kind of like really uh
he has an amazing laugh it sounds like
kind of avoids
falling down a drain and it's sort of
like kind of implodes
on itself and he's um he's a really very
happy man somehow
and uh yeah he's
i don't know i mean it's it's
interesting because i i suppose that
that now seems like quite a long time
ago
to i was translating all of batu's work
on um samuel beckett
and working with alberto toscano who i
was in a relationship
at that time for for a decade and we're
still friends um
yeah and i was kind of very committed to
this
project of translating kind of lots of
the contemporary french
thinkers who were talking about
ideas of i mean well love in baju's case
in relation to
to beckett and he had he has this very
platonic reading of
samuel beckett in which beckett is kind
of reducing uh
being to its kind of fundamental
dimensions it's a very kind of like
purified
image of beckett and i was very drawn to
this idea and i
i love samuel beckett so much
particularly how it is and the later
beckett
where the prose becomes kind of
completely um
uh primordial and you know like you use
this word
like sonic a lot like this idea of a
kind of earthy
um
and but that brings me to the tie
naturally
i've been reading a secret society
transmission books
um i i'm just in awe of these people all
getting together to have these talks and
nature with one another and to
meet minds that were so similar
when there is traditionally so much
fighting on the left but to form like
this higher
you know um mental spiritual connection
um with the battalion society and i'm
curious to hear
what you think about the battalion
society
um yeah i mean i'm like this idea of a
secret society i think is that
like really really important um
incredibly
interesting and all kinds of levels i
mean i think our current situation
you know like something like this for
example is kind of post academic or para
academic or
you know uh parallel to in any kind of
formal institutional structure and i
think you know this is the world we're
kind of heading into the course i
i ran with justin murphy on but i was a
kind of you know absolutely this sort of
you know experimental thing we're both
former academics who left
for various reasons you know partly to
do the desire for freedom partly because
we were
getting kind of in trouble uh for other
reasons
and you know i mean to to try to do
these new things i mean at the same time
there's obviously a kind of huge
tension brought up by figures like a
gambin in his you know
actually very perhaps hyperbolic
criticism of zoom
you know he's kind of comparing the use
of zoom to almost kind of like fascist
uh um modes of being you know as if as
if we are
you know what we're turning our back on
when we're doing things like this
uh you know what we're losing is the
proximity
is the kind of social interaction you
know the the face to face
um and i think that that must also be
born in mind you know that there is
whatever happens well you know obviously
i think it's
better that these things happen that
they don't
but they can't they're not the same and
they can't replace
let's say an intimate you know social
scene and so the question of the secret
society
i think whether we're talking about
online or off you know
clearly i mean what's what strikes me
about what but i and the others
and kozovsky and others were up to at
that time is
trying to push the limits of what's
possible within a kind of agreement so
the kind of
the idea that you have a loyalty and a
bond and whatever happens within the
society and it's not even about doing
scandalous things necessarily people get
hung up on the human sacrifice
idea but i think that's the
i don't think that's the interesting
aspect of what they were doing i think
what they were trying to do is actually
push a kind of collective
thought a sort of um group mental
process
who's um esoteric aspects had to be
protected
in order for the esoteric to to then be
able to thrive i mean because asifa was
also
kind of exoteric you know as in an
outward looking
um thing as well with the mag with the
journal
you know and i and i do think i mean
raven gave a very nice talk in there but
i caused about how for example like
marriage could be conceived as a secret
society
and i really like this idea you know
because it actually kind of
repositions something that we might
criticize
as a traditional structure as something
that's kind of you know
oppressive and you know should be
transcended and it reposes it as
something potentially much more like
intriguing and um and secret
and i actually really i thought that was
really uh interesting and i
i kind of agree i do think you know that
that need for the uh
the the private and the kind of uh
esoteric whether we're thinking with
others
you know and who we're talking to and
what we're talking about i mean you know
the older i get the more i value
um an ongoing dialogue with certain
people who i respect intellectually i
find this is
one of the most kind of beautiful things
about
remaining alive you know these kind of
things
wow yeah i would actually want to know
who is your favorite
famous or not goodness modern
philosopher
um what you person was somebody i
respect
is the modern modern thinker
um yeah sorry someone's just asking who
spoke of marriage well it was raven
who's hosting one of the co-hosts
um steph it was so raven you can
probably fill in
steph at some point yeah about this idea
that was my this and i'm working on
kind of developing that idea uh using pi
and and also thinking about uh issues
that i think even your poem brings up
which is like a kind of alienation and
of connection to nature
and you just brought this up in the
sense of like proximity right because
all of these ways in which this
particularly now
we are finding ourselves in intimate
relationships with one another are
mediated through
this uh this technological force which
is
inherently a manipulative it's in it's
inherently withdrawn manipulative uh
entity that we are interacting with and
interfacing with
in order to have these most precious
uh aspects of the human experience and
that's why i was thinking
um in the sense of like we've lost
we've lost so much already in terms of
the ground of the human experience that
we have to go back to the most
basic form of bonding
and secrecy which is the dyad is the
most basic form i mean you have the
internal world
obviously um which can be your own
secret
realm but in a sense like at least from
my perspective
the individual is a kind of illusion um
that we've moved to be primary in in
this kind of
contemporary sense but really we are of
of a collective
and the individual is a kind of emergent
property of the collective
so to try and to reform um bonds that
are long-standing you spoke of like
these relationships that you've had
throughout your life that are now
like i mean they become more the most
precious things that you have
and to kind of reform and re-understand
and revitalize the notion of marriage
as kind of a revolutionary act where you
are
sealing off to the outside and you are
protecting a zone
where the forces of technology cannot
penetrate where the forces
of identity you know kind of what you're
talking about earlier anita about how
identity is this kind of like
thing out there that you like put on
yourself and you contort yourself
into this like house exterior form um
it's about presenting yourself to the
world and about like kind of
like almost curating a kind of celebrity
or kind of brand
like you push that out outside of your
membrane and in time
and in the inside you have this like
secret world that's kind of how i
have been thinking about um this notion
of marriage
yeah no i think that's really beautiful
and actually i do i do agree that like
in the in the age of kind of tinder and
the algorithm deciding who you should
date that actually um to to be loyal and
and you know i mean to use badger in
language like to be faithful if you like
have fidelity to an event let's say the
love event you know to to be with
someone to decide actually to
you know spend your life with somebody
is does actually now appear
not not so much domestic tyranny but
rather a radical and revolutionary act
and i think
even zizek was making this point you
know about 10 15 years ago
you know rather than the kind of
absolute and you know
interchangeability of the other in which
you're kind of constantly moving through
random others which i think kind of
absolutely um
you know evacuates everybody of their
uniqueness
in a way so i mean just to to answer
like rachel's question about kind of
contemporary
thinkers i mean it it occurs to me that
really in a
of a piece with what we're saying it's
it's really my peers
who i respect more i mean of course
there are kind of older
figures who i you know admire who are
still alive you know including a gambin
and baju and and others but actually the
i i would say the most kind of
interesting and
and moving discussions are with people
who are i don't know i mean more or less
of similar
cohort or younger you know that that the
act of thinking i mean the philosophical
dialogue itself is what's important it's
it's it's maybe
the older you get it's less about having
a particular master
or a particular figure that one follows
and reads up but rather
it's having the dialogue with particular
people
you know or it doesn't have to be two
but yeah like we keep coming back to the
dialogue and i think
yeah absolutely the the esoteric aspect
you know walking with your friend in
nature
and discussing spinoza or something i
mean you know what's more beautiful
really than this so yeah i think my
my peers would be my favorite
philosophers
today i think it's amazing that
we're able to find peer groups like this
they think of the
ccru and the uk and
the tax society and what people are
doing right now and
secret societies i mean they've been
given a bad name
by some people um but what do you think
is the
end goal of a secret society is it a
way to heretically
communicate to succeed to
create a utopia what what is that
it's just an exploration of those bonds
itself i mean i think the the act of
mutually agreeing with other people to
preserve a particular space
you know you can think of it as a kind
of yeah a secret society or a cartel or
a dyad or a
you know or a dialogic partner you know
in a way it's it's both closed and open
so i mean i think one of the things that
i
really you know noticed that was
happening again over the past 10 years
and and you know one of the negative
things i think that was happening in the
in the left
at least in london and the london art
world and so on
was um in a sense a kind of very
abstract or even absent notion of
friendship or loyalty like those things
just kind of
weren't there anymore there was a kind
of dispensability of
people you know where people had if they
transgressed or said or did the wrong
thing people were kind of
um you know expelled increasingly in
this kind of mechanism
um as kind of scapegoating mechanism and
as if there was some other abstract
world in which
uh you know the left was working towards
and it wasn't just
a load of people it wasn't just everyone
who was there and
and it just kind of became more obvious
to me that no
that we are all we have you know there
there isn't some other thing that we can
dispense with each other
in order to you know uh be more in favor
of
it's we have to work with each other and
you know to imagine that you can just
kind of dispense with people in this way
was actually extremely kind of
destructive so
i kind of had a revelation about things
like loyalty and friendship
in a very real and concrete way and
about the meaningfulness of those things
you know these are not um
minor things these are absolutely kind
of um crucial central things that
actually sustain
a life and a you know a
thoughtful existence um
so yeah yeah
how do you think that um alienation
works its way into the history of men
versus the history of women
and how that shows up today with this
kind of atomization process
of kind of living in a techno-capitalist
world
yeah i think that's a really interesting
question i mean i've been working a lot
in the last two years on the
um discretion of of men rather than
women
right so i've written this book called
what do men want which is a kind of
jokey reference to
freud's question what does woman want
and so i reposed it
to about men and and obviously there's
been a lot of discussion about
you know a very negative discussion
about men in the last few years
you know these ideas of toxic
masculinity and this idea that kind of
men are somehow like
uh i don't know fatally like awful
thing um which has been kind of
promulgated by very liberal media
um you know at the same time it also a
kind of fear
of of of a resurgence or a kind of
particular kind of masculinity which is
then associated with the dissident right
or the
alt-right or in cells or so on so i kind
of looked at all these sort of phenomena
and the way in which they kind of play
out
in the discourse and it actually ended
up being a book about the relationship
between men and women
so it's actually really in the end a
book about how men and women get along
and the kind of games and interactions
that they have in a very mixed
world because after all our kind of
contemporary world is a very
heterosocial
one right which is to say not a
heterosexual one although sometimes it
is that as well but
primarily it's a world in which men and
women work together
they see each other on the street it's
not a segregated world it's a very very
um
intricate world which has caused kind of
a lot of problems
and fears and anxieties perhaps because
there is so much proximity
um and you know particularly after
things like me too it's obvious that
there
is a great deal of anxiety around things
like sexual approaches
and you know lots of people used to meet
their partner
or their future wife or husband at work
and i think
now you know many people would be
extremely
um anxious about um you know any form of
kind of
flirtation or romantic interaction with
people
in a work environment so there's a kind
of you know a suspicion and
a hostility that's kind of been um
really uh exacerbated in the past few
years
um and i tried to think about what it
might mean to actually kind of reconcile
in a kind of fun and playful way
um so in terms of alienation i suppose
i'm interested in like yeah i guess
actually probably like a collective
project that would involve both men and
women
you know just in trying to work out
exactly what's going on and how we can
be together
and how we can live together in this
kind of complicated way i'm not
interested
in it's very complicated because i mean
obviously i do think that
men and women are different right you
know i do think there are important
differences
but at the same time i think there is a
collective social and intellectual and
emotional and romantic and even
friendship project
that is possible you know and that
indeed happens you know men and women
are friends
you know despite the ideas of the
country
and so i do think there's a kind of
shared um
a shared project which is actually quite
beautiful and
and strange and interesting in that we
can work out together
whether it's in marriage or friendship
or you know
collectively socially and in fact i
think we kind of have to do that i think
the idea that we're so
opposed you know is um and that men are
somehow
you know irredeemably flawed is
extremely
untrue and extremely unhelpful i don't
think that is the
experience that most women have of most
men
right it's not to say that there aren't
some terrible things that happen
right and we're all capable of terrible
things we're all we've all
done harm we've all hurt people we've
all upset people we've all behaved
badly we've all said things that have
you know
you know caused real damage and the
older you get i think the more you
learn to live with that and you
understand that and i think
we live in a a very weird post-christian
period in
socially which is to say we have the
kind of almost like an old testament
you know desire to punish each other but
without the
forgiveness you know
so people are very very kind of um quick
to
say well this person did or said that
but they're much much less
uh amenable to forgiveness and and i
think we can't really proceed without
forgiveness
right it's not to say that we shouldn't
recognize harm where it's where it's
occurred
but i think you know we have often this
kind of very cold vigilante
understanding and you know obviously the
internet has become a very
brutal tool in the punishment and use
circulation of names if you want to
accuse someone of something you know
it's absolutely blunt you don't know
where your
your accusation is going to end up when
it often does a lot of damage
to people so i tried to look at all of
these kinds of um
things and and suggest a more kind of
yeah like uh reconciled and playful and
and intellectual and thoughtful way of
being together
that does address alienation you know of
different kinds
i suppose i didn't read it
yeah it really does um
so we're kind of at the halfway point so
if people want to throw chat
uh questions in and we will uh look at
your questions and
you can meet yourself and ask your
question directly to nita or
me or rachel um but i wanted to
i'm gonna want to keep kind of riffing
on this
um what you just presented here which is
like
i think there seems to be a struggle
with pluralism
we seem to be struggling with the idea
that there are different kinds of people
who need different kinds of things
and that maybe there would be pockets of
people
who would be appealing to certain people
based on their certain kind of desire
for those certain kinds of things
and there's a desire like it seems for
certain factions to devour
preferences of other factions and this
seems to be
the case with maybe something like the
idea of like polyamory versus
monogamy right like there's this kind of
war about like
you know which mating strategy is better
or dating strategy is better and it's
like well
what about the possibility that for some
people polyamory works and for some
people monogamy works and that
would be philosophical intellectual
romantic
like cultures and movements that appeal
to those two
microcosms of of existence and that the
one needing to devour the other
is is like kind of a moot point so what
do you what do you think about this
this like lack of of pluralism that we
have in the culture
um yeah i mean i think
in practice things are very pluralist i
think people
do live in very different life worlds
and you know i mean
you know i i agree about polygamy and
do i mean polygamy polyamory
polygamy that's not generally engaged in
many ways but no no like polyamory yeah
i mean i know some people in
who are into polyamory and you know i
kind of i understand what they're saying
when they talk about it you know
they seem very rational and very kind of
thoughtful and it's all very kind of
discursive and it's all very
you know worked out um i mean i think i
think the poetic
uh you know tragic side of me
can't bear the idea of like having a
google spreadsheet
type relationship to to other people
i'd rather suffer and like you know uh
write poetry
and be romantic and um you know so so i
in a way i don't yeah it's not for
everybody right it's like people
of like you say i mean some people are
more into monogamy some people
you know polyamory i i don't
particularly carry the way i mean i do
think they're probably broader cultural
comments we could make about um
what what is kind of revealed in the
popularity or
why some people might be pushing things
like polyamory you know is it a kind of
um yeah
[Music]
this is the cause and my impression
as another old left person is that
they took houses and capitalized on them
and they turned
the cro to the big money they did every
time
um so how do you tell
when something is organic now
like for any social activist movements
at all like i got
by from the social activism community
but i know like
some people they just talk to their
friends and not everybody in that
community
is bad but there does seem to be like a
shutdown of discussion
how how would you like as an intelligent
woman
deal with these people in an effective
way
i mean well i don't know i mean whether
we're talking about this particular
thing or not i mean i
i mean one thing that just becomes
clearer and clearer to me the older i
get
and the further away i get from
particular institutions and groups is
is in the first place the absolute um
priority of thinking for oneself
you know of preserving one's own mind
you know and to actually
ask yourself whatever you're thinking
about or reading or talking
about you know to ask yourself in the
first place well what do i think
you know before you then start to think
oh well what does this person think or
what should i think or what's the right
thing to think or what are most people
saying
you know i mean it's so basic but i mean
it seemed to take me a really long time
to learn this in certain ways and i
think
there's also a kind of often like a
female socialization
thing which is about being nice and you
know it's quite hard to resist that sort
of training
um you know where you don't want to
upset people
and actually sometimes saying what you
think is going to cause um
upset um and then asking that question
of whether
it's worth saying what you think because
you know it's going to cause trouble or
or keeping quiet becomes like quite um
a major one so i don't know i mean again
i think this is just
a sort of existential lesson that
perhaps i learned as well and and also
kind of recovering from
being a you know quite hardcore
alcoholic and then just waking up
and going like oh my god what have i
been doing for 20 years
and suddenly realizing in a way
that even though i'd been kind of
thinking and working and doing all this
this stuff
and you know whether it was you know
writing essays or
activism or whatever teaching that in a
way some sort of basic
things i hadn't quite articulated or
grounded for myself which would be to do
with this freedom
to think independently first of all
and i think because also the the sort of
leftist project
in a way it depends upon a certain
putting
an abstract notion of the collective
first as if
you know the individual is not really
relevant you know or that your
feelings or thoughts are kind of
secondary um
to whatever the the group think is
and i think that's very common for
almost any kind of
dominant group in a way um
so to like reclaim your own mind first
of all seems to be
major step
yeah i've been feeling that way like
very strongly because
you know i think that there's so many uh
maybe if we're being generous like kind
of archetypes or um
concepts of what it means to actualize
that are being sold to you
essentially um kind of competing for
your attention and so as an individual
it's hard to know what's yours
and what's someone else's and there's a
kind of necessity
to take on the question of becoming
i think you spoke with that earlier with
the kind of second wave feminist kind of
notion of like
becoming oneself kind of arising into
who you are
throughout the entirety of your life
cycle you know because that continuously
transforms over the course of someone's
life
and that continual becoming
uh and that introspective process i
think is
crucial for i mean i think it's a
political act i literally
like i really think it's a revolutionary
political act
to engage from oneself and to ask
oneself and and not in a solid cystic
way and i think maybe that's a good
question because there's so much
solipsism
in a lot of like new age thinking like
this kind of
weird health guru thing so how do we
like turn into ourselves and really ask
these difficult questions about who are
we becoming without falling into the
trap
of solipsism and narcissism
no sure i mean in a way i think this
capacity to think or like
you know sort of re-reasserting
that basic empty category of thought is
in a way it doesn't have necessarily
having even any content it's simply a
potential it's like well
i couldn't think it's like i mean this
is why philosophy is always
going back to absolutely fundamental
things or foundational questions
constantly
and in a way philosophy seems to me
nothing other on some level
than the reposing endlessly of
incredibly simple
you know forms of openness and wonder to
the very act of thinking itself and
and that kind of always has to be born
in mind so so i would say even before
this kind of content
of like the self or particular things
that one is thinking
it's to do with that kind of um capacity
itself
um and that's what that kind of needs to
be kind of
preserved or protected and so i mean i i
don't know in a weird way i want to say
like one is not even herself or
not even an individual at that level you
know it's
it's almost like the cartesian thing of
like you know it's like okay i think
therefore i am but it's not even
i mean descartes even says too much i
what he should say is there is there is
thinking you know that there is
thought happening and it's a kind of um
capacity
so you know i i mean i know what you
mean and i think there's
a lot of political resistance to the
idea of individual
thinking you know that actually needs to
also be overcome i mean i also
um you know did psychoanalysis for three
years and and actually like
you know i'm still in analysis and and
getting over that guilt of even talking
about
oneself as if there's anything
interesting to say
about it and and actually there both is
and there isn't
it's kind of like well you're no more or
less interesting than anyone or anything
else
right um and in a way it's not even
about
you it's like whatever that means it's
kind of
you know there is a a process there is a
structure
there is a way in which you sort of came
to be who you are or in the process of
becoming
and there's actually something kind of
very interesting about
understanding that and actually that
opens you up to the world
again you know that it that it doesn't
necessarily or hopefully become a
narcissistic or solipsistic project but
actually what it does is kind of break
you away from those things precisely so
that you can be more
in the world and more with other people
and more thoughtful and more expansive
so i think both philosophy and
psychoanalysis if we want to say that
have that as a kind of breaking open
into the world you know that it's not a
confirmation there's nothing positive
necessarily about it i mean
psychoanalysis is famously not there to
make you feel better
you know it doesn't teach you how to be
happy or anything like that
nor does philosophy exactly
oh great be happy maybe
you need to be more interesting speaking
of interesting i've been looking at
some very interesting questions and
comments in this chat
um hello kante would you like to unmute
yourself and read this question
yeah sure which one because i put a lot
of them in there yeah you've worked with
um uh
you've worked with budo uh nina and uh
yuva i'm not sure you've probably read
loads of uh
jack and hegel but the question is um
would you say almost uh because you were
in the battalion i was never really in
the
in the course for that but uh one
example of a feminine
femininity that is always referred to as
the antigone myth
and that kind of conspiracy between
antigone and ismane
and i was just wondering like what you
thought about like almost like what's
the modern
version of that or how how would that be
interpreted in today's light especially
given the fact that i know
one of one of our things raven talks was
the importance of motherhood
whereas in taken he's traditionally seen
as a figure who's kind of against the
idea of motherhood and that's what she's
trying to like
almost be against by committing the act
when she does
um yeah no sure i mean there's loads of
things to say about antigone and her
relation to the state and to justice
and so on i mean like i mean before his
death recently bernard stiegler was
talking about greta thunder as a kind of
antigone
figure right so i mean it's quite it's
kind of quite strange i mean
what whatever we think about about this
idea but but
you know the idea of kind of um the
the female figure opposing if you like
the kind of
um you know in anger like it's a
particularly
um effective mode of being right to
oppose the
the state law and to say that there are
laws that are more important or there
are kind of
um forms of justice that are more
important than the laws of the
the state you know so antigone is
positioned always as this kind of figure
who you know in her desire to bury her
brother
you know and and to kind of perform
these burial rites
against what she's ordered to do and
she'll do that
at the risk and cost of her own
extinction
because that's what she's committed to
so it's a kind of um
you know she's a kind of heroic figure
obviously in this way
you know and she poses the possibility
of a kind of thought and being outside
of
what the laws are what we're supposed to
do um
no and in that sense she's kind of like
a perennial figure of thought
and being you know that that
you know exists as a possibility for for
anyone
in a way or not for anyone but i mean
potentially for anyone like can anyone
be antigone
perhaps you know it's like a possibility
um in particular circumstances perhaps
so i mean what i mean one thing i
suppose that
maybe is quite lacking today in many
ways is the kind of idea of tragedy
you know we live in a world that's kind
of obviously very
technocratic technological progressive
in lots of ways
very positivistic very scientific
you know that that even in the face of a
kind of global pandemic and what could
be an opportunity to rethink
um values and death in particular i mean
this is kind of again what gambin was
was saying that that actually it's it
still remains at the level often of a
very uh you know statistical
political technocratic discourse right
there hasn't
necessarily been a rethinking or
opening up of these deeper questions
about the value of life and death
you know and the reality of of death you
know i mean
when we talk about extinction and the
possibility environmentally or
globally in relation to some you know
like a
like the pandemic of course it raises
this question of
human extinction um
you know are we able as a society to
think
about about tragedy and about fate in
the same way that the greeks
might might have done i don't think so
you know tragedy seems to have
disappeared in into
you know it seems to have dissolved
right into this kind of technocratic
image of death in which death is simply
another
hygienic possibility for being you know
and it's kind of hidden away
um so i mean figures like antigone
perhaps
point to a different relation to death
right i mean of course they do
you know to to want to to and again
again they talked about burial rights
he was very very opposed to the idea
that people would no longer be able to
bury
they're dead and to be there in ritual
ways you know in ceremonial ways
so yeah
yes no sacrifice yeah exactly
ritual and also the the banning
of those that came before you not you
but like the general act
of people starting something
together that they're really passionate
about and then
many people come in don't really get it
but they're just really good at mimicry
and they work their way up you know um
and academia
did you ever feel like these people
were against you or did you just find a
way
to get along with them did you play the
game like how do you operate
in that frame um yeah but i mean i was a
lecturer for 13 years
i mean i think things shifted once the
because obviously we had the fee regime
in britain that
you know so the fee we lost the battle
to stop their fees becoming very high so
they were 9
000 pounds a year so students were
ending up with in 50 000 pounds worth of
debt
you know more like the american model
and um
you know i i i think it became i mean
you know where i was teaching was not an
elite institution so my students were
often coming from working-class
backgrounds and they were often
working while they were studying and the
cost
in every sense of doing a degree was was
very high and the anxiety that it would
it was inducing was very very high and i
and i felt that it became harder and
harder and less moral
to be a teacher in that environment you
know to actually support this system
of mass debt um you know
you know the mass induction of debt uh
in us in a system in which people were
not going to get jobs that were
worthy of their intellect in fact
following the degree um
so i don't know i mean i was never
really i mean i'm sort of
yeah i was a good academic in some ways
and a really bad academic in other ways
i think
most academics are personally very
socially conservative
even if they work on like you know
revolutionary stuff or whatever
they're actually very um you know
uh careful um about how they behave
because a lot of people don't obviously
don't want to lose their job
um so they they you know i think
academia became very inhibited and we
see
that more and more like i think there's
a lot of fear in academia of
speaking about particular issues and a
lot of academics just keep their head
down
which isn't very good for a productive
intellectual environment right like
you what you want is people who are free
to to think and to speak and to do work
that might actually you know tell you
things that people don't want to know
you know
to push the boat out to to actually
yeah say dangerous and difficult things
not just for the sake of it but because
they might be true
um you know and i think that that became
harder and harder
for everybody um and i do think
contemporary academia
is over i i think those institutions
many of them are going to fall they're
going to collapse
as a result of kobe but they were
already kind of over
um in many many ways ideologically
because they were kind of
screwed um you know because of this kind
of fear and the dominance of particular
ways of speaking and i don't think it
was kind of everywhere but
it was it was getting bad definitely
um and students themselves were becoming
afraid to speak in seminars you know i
really noticed this as the years went on
they they were afraid in case they said
the wrong thing and that they would get
punished by their peers
and a lot of students were on you know
quite a lot of antidepressants they were
often
you know in very bad mental states
really
um and it was really quite sad and awful
to see that
and there was very little really you can
do as a you know
random lecturer about that so there was
a kind of general
negative climate um i would say and so
the question then becomes what comes
after and i think after a plague
there's usually like a renaissance you
know cultural renaissance so i think a
lot of the old institutions whether
they're academic or artistic
or whatever all of these big things a
lot of them are going to have to
radically change or they're going to
fall
apart and people are going to start
doing much more of their own thing
um and i actually think and i think
maybe justin makes this argument
that the elites are actually going to
abandon a lot of the
elite institutions and set up their own
as well you know that actually they'll
just hand them over
um two people who give chair random
meaningless chairs and positions
to people in order to appear gracious
and woke but actually they're going to
carry on doing their own thing
elsewhere so
yeah we have a good question from dan we
actually have a few
questions from dan feldman in the chat
dan do you want to mute yourself and
ask your questions um sure
but uh can you copy one of the questions
i don't
i haven't been following raven i have a
question which one did you like best
um i think that this one where would you
expect this discourse to open up to the
more metaphysical approach
is interesting and then also the one
before which was oh
jealousy is related to fear there are
cognitive
practices that can dissolve fear but
this is a side discussion in some way to
the discussions of polyamory i think the
more interesting question
is this what needs are people attempting
to meet by participating in polyamory
versus pairing versus aestheticism
what are the biggest underserved needs
in this meeting crisis
i'm going to roof on that and then yeah
that's i think you did just
we'll just go you you did well thank you
um nina i'll i'll repost the question if
you want to look
you know i can see them i can see them
i'll scroll back up um yeah i mean
they're two slightly different ones i
don't know dan
would you want to sort of focus on
on one um
i mean i guess to riffing off of your
comments
that that we've lost the sense of
tragedy in society i mean it's
it's to me it's an aesthetically
um blind ignorant dumb
society where 80
of what it means to be human is not
reflected in
in the minds and the souls of the people
running the society
um and i would argue that that's a lack
a lack of you know considering
philosophical or metaphysical issues to
begin with
um
i'm trying to tie this together into a
question um
well okay here here's the question uh
you're mentioning that the academia and
the universities are sort of collapsing
and there's going to be probably some
kind of a
a flight from them into what i'm
starting to see and i'm wondering if
you're starting to see this
is some kind of embedded uh learning
ecosystems
where learning institutions perhaps
completely unrelated to the historical
learning institutions will start
seed forms will start appearing and they
will be
embedded tightly into the community and
it
it'll be a more organic form a more
organic complex uh emergent form
of learning and education
that is focused i'm hoping on
actually solving the problems that the
old system created
and i'm wondering if you have any any
thoughts or ideas of whether
you're seeing anything in that yeah i
mean i i think you know i think people
want to learn and talk to each other i
mean you know like on on some level we
have access
you know if you have access to the
internet to the entire history of
existing
texts right i mean that you know it's
possible to get hold of everything
that's
more or less that's been kind of
preserved of human
production right so on some level like
there's a kind of
immense richness of things that can be
revisited read together discussed and so
on and i think
yeah i mean i think people have always
spontaneously organized or
taught themselves and you know thought
together in
you know auto didactic ways or kind of
working-class
ways or you know that so i think that's
not going to stop i mean i think
obviously the technology does allow for
kind of multiple platform use in
different ways and
you know i mean it's going to it's going
to be interesting
how much people can meet in person you
know i mean i think we're probably
heading into another lock down here
as well i mean not not clear exactly yet
but i
it's you know those sorts of things are
maybe you know clearly becoming much
more pressurized and people have lot
you know completely different attitudes
to whether they are want to be outside
with other people or not like there's a
really huge psychological
difference in how people react anxiously
or otherwise to these um
rules or laws it's not even clear what
they are
um and so yeah i mean i think i think
there will be all of these kind of
as you say like learning ecosystems um
that are more community based i think i
think you're yeah you're going to get
more like
patchworks of different kind of
intellectual desires i mean you already
do
like in forums and and so on you know
people are kind of drawn
all over the place right so those ways
of mapping
what interests people i mean i think i
mean the kind of more boring
institutional question would be
like what happens to accreditation right
because obviously people can run around
learning whatever they like
you know and that's great and often
people are highly motivated to do that
much more so than if they think they
have to get a degree in order to do
something else
but you know when if institutions kind
of collapse and then you just
end up with lots more para academic or
kind of semi-academic things
then the question about accreditation
then becomes an issue like what is a
degree worth is it worth
anything you know does it matter if you
have one or not i mean
what are there even any jobs is there a
kind of economy that
in which that would make sense anymore
um and i
think those are like perhaps massive and
really difficult to answer questions at
this point
um but i think in the meantime the
desire to know and to learn
will absolutely um you know persist and
i i think people will
yeah more and more realize that they are
capable you know that it's possible to
do
these things i mean people were mocking
people for starting podcasts during the
um the lockdown but actually i think
like why not i mean why not people have
podcasts to discuss whatever they want
and if people are interested in the same
things they can listen to that podcast
and maybe
every podcast will have like one or two
listeners
but but why not this is like this is
already very beautiful like
not everything has to appeal to the
largest number of people all the time
it's never going to
you know people make their own kind of
worlds and communities and
secret societies you know so
definitely and the stella is kind of one
of those
yeah exactly it's a really you know
impressively organized one i mean given
the
the range of speakers you have is
incredible
yeah i always spoken back home yeah
you're one of us
i actually wanted to ask you
uh about embodiment i know it's very big
in these communities to discuss
environment but i also know i'm
as someone who's also studied market
fisher and nick lands that
there is not a disembodied philosophy
that is directly engaging with the mind
and not the body
and i'm curious if you will get crap
from other women
for like having philosophers you like
that aren't
embodied enough and just this kind of
like male female energy
dynamic does this kind of thing go on
with your
peers and how how does that work
um i i don't know i mean i don't i don't
think there's
too much of that kind of um criticism
going on i mean i i i don't know i mean
i suppose just just personally it was a
kind of revelation to like
get fit and work out and and
realize like how much mentally better i
felt
and that this was actually very positive
for my
you know philosophical thinking as well
you know and it's actually kind of
interesting
to reflect on that kind of relationship
between mind and body in that way
um just on some very basic personal
level i suppose and and
you know to revisit someone like spinoza
for example you know who says like
thought and extension and basically two
different ways of looking at the same
thing
you know there's a kind of parallelism
you know it's a very different
it's not kind of mind-body split that
then needs to be put back together it's
that
you know it's a slightly different way
of understanding the
the two you know as as one in a certain
way you know that they're kind of the
same thing just seen
under different attributes and yes i
said i know i mean i think yeah i wonder
what's what's going on with the
embodiment discussion
at the moment i mean certainly there's
kind of lots of questions about how
disembodied people are like the virtual
the you know the online you know i mean
when i was doing the research about
masculinity and men obviously they're
kind of
question of like men working out came up
a lot you know like the kind of
uh big celebration of kind of uh gym
you know going to the gym and working
out and and that kind of thing
um you know came up a lot and it was
actually very very interesting and i
kind of defend that in the book
um as it were you know to say well why
why how is it not a positive thing
that people that men look after their
bodies rather than
like lie around eating chips and
watching porn you know
surely it's a good thing that people
take care of themselves you know it's
better for
everyone uh that people are fitter right
and and
you know go outside and so i don't know
i mean it's um
on the kind of male female question
yeah i i don't know i think i think i'm
suspicious of people who would
um be critical of
being healthy and fit i think there's
sometimes a little bit of a
negative attitude towards that um on the
left and and
in particular and uh that's wrong i'm
against that
yeah well nina we're kind of at the hour
yeah i am so grateful that you could
come and join us and
discuss all of these myriad topics it's
been a really wonderful
story yeah it's been amazing and
uh do you just any final words any
things we should be looking out for
in your in your sphere things that
you're doing conversations you're having
um yeah i don't know i mean i'm i'm
starting to
to think i'm doing this course on the
philosophy of risk which is the
next kind of big topic i'm kind of
thinking about um
and that was in relation partly to the
pandemic it was partly this question as
i was saying about different people's
psychological attitudes you know like
actually how do human beings calculate
their own relation to risk and
probability so i wanted to actually
start
you know i'm teaching this course it's
an adult ed course in the uk
um about these kind of questions right
so
so because it struck me as very
interesting that you had in some
situations you could see people
being very authoritative or even
authoritarian about the rules
but sometimes they would break the rules
and and actively break the rules like
to go on a black lives matter protest
because they valued that more
right so you had this kind of often like
really massive sea change in people's
perspective and evaluation of their own
relation to risk or the collective risk
so i wanted to then just go through like
those concepts
in this course so yeah that's one big
thing
i'm working on and yeah the finishing
the man book basically just doing the
final edits and
probably writing more controversial
articles
than a telegraph because i needed to
make some money uh defending
jk rowling and the right to write
fiction about whatever
she wants and anyone wants and uh you
know getting lots of
people sending me horrible gore pictures
and nasty messages
but it's fine you know people can do
that too if they're like
so wait yeah
when your book is released i think this
will be a nice uh
jumping-off point for many more yeah
hopefully next year at some point
it takes a while because it's like a big
publisher and i can't just put it out
in a week like the other thing that that
rachel was reading from before
very diy yeah
great all right well thank you so much
nina and uh
we'll see you around the store yeah
all right thank you thank you i couldn't
answer all the questions there are lots
of things coming up and uh
yes i'll come back again all right
thank you and with that i'm going to
just uh inform
people about some future events that are
coming up at the stoa
it's going to be a pretty fascinating
week
we have coming right up meta modern
masculinity a good pair
to this conversation that we're having
here about a femininity with aaron
rodgerson
that's september 20th at 6 00 pm eastern
time highly recommend those
conversations i've been watching them
and they're very engaging
then also we have the fourth political
theory with alexander dugan
that's on the 21st at noon eastern time
and that day we have stacked right so we
have taking his thoughts wherever they
go with derek jensen right after that
that's going to be on 4 p.m eastern time
and then
unity 2020 with brett weinstein it's
going to be at 6 30 p.m that day
uh and there's so much more so please
check the website the stoa.ca
to get a look at all of the future
events
coming up here at the stoa and thank you
all so much for being here
much gratitude